Register of the Semen Dmitrievich Ignat'ev Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Semen Dmitrievich Ignat'ev papers,
1898-1976
2000C62
Hoover Institution Archives
6 microfilm reels (0.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, financial records, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Russian choirs in the United States.
Ignat'ev, Semen Dmitrievich, 1891-1974
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
S. D. Ignat'ev was born near the town of Ostrov, Pskovskaia guberniia, on 25 January 1891 (O. S.). While in the White army in South Russia, he married Aleksandra Ivanovna Kozlova, thus cementing his association with the Kuban' Cossacks. Evacuation to Gallipoli was followed by several years in Bulgaria.
A musician by training, he formed a chorus and musical ensemble of émigré Kuban' Cossacks around 1926, touring with them across Europe through the 1940s. During these years, he lived primarily in Germany, and in one of his writings describes his experiences in Berlin in 1945. The Second World War brought about the dissolution of the Kuban' Cossack Chorus. In 1950, Ignat'ev moved to Sweden (where he found employment mounting specimens for the botanical department of the Swedish Museum of Natural History), and then in 1955 to San Francisco, changing his musical venue to conducting church choirs (his education included the Pskov seminary, where he received a thorough grounding in liturgical music). Ignat'ev died in San Francisco in May 1974
Chronology
1891 January 25 Born, Ostrovskii uezd, Pskovskaia guberniia, Russia
1918 June 8 Married Aleksandra Ivanovna Kozlova, Gul'kevichi village, Kubanskaia oblast'
1920 Evacuated to Gallipoli with White Army
c. 1926 Organized Kuban' Cossack Chorus
1950 Emigrated to Sweden
1955 Emigrated to the United States
1961 Naturalized as a U.S. citizen
1974 Died, San Francisco, California
Scope and Content Note
Semen Dmitrievich Ignat'ev was well-known as a composer and conductor of the Kuban' Cossack Chorus, and later of church choirs. This collection consists mainly of materials relating to these activities. Other subjects include autobiographical writings dealing with his experiences on Gallipoli in the early 1920s and in Berlin in 1945, as well as writings, subject files and printed matter relating to Russian Orthodox liturgical music. Some of the correspondence is with relatives in the Soviet Union.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming of these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain at the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table of corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Choral societies--United States.; Russia.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1910-1972 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Address book, articles, congratulatory notes, contracts, identity papers, letters of recommendation, school records, scrapbook, and miscellany arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1926-1976 (Box 1-3)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1917-1966 (Box 3-5)
  Arranged chronologically by title. Includes musical compositions
- Subject File, 1927-1974 (Box 5-6)
  Correspondence, leaflets, notes and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Printed Matter, 1898-1974 (Box 7)
  Bulletins, clippings and periodicals, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Relates to Cossacks, Russian culture, military history and miscellaneous subjects
- Pnotographs, c. 1910-1974 (Box 8-10)
  Albums and individual photographs of Ignat'ev, his wife, his chorus, as well as other figures (mostly unidentified) and places
- Artwork, n.d. (Box 10)
  One watercolor painting of a pastoral scene
- Financial Records, 1927-1974 (Box 10)
  Bank records, receipts, financial calculations, tax forms. Not filmed
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1910-1972 (Box 1)
  - Address book (Folder 1: 1)
  - Articles about or mentioning Ignat'ev (Folder 1: 2)
  - Congratulatory notes honoring Ignat'ev and his chorus (Folder 1: 3)
  - Contract (Folder 1: 4)
  - Family file -- Aleksandra Ignat'eva
    - Identity papers (Folder 1: 5)
    - School records (Folder 1: 6)
  - Identity papers. (Folder 1: 7)
    Includes naturalization and marriage certificates, residence, work and travel permits
  - Letters of recommendation for Ignat'ev (Folder 1: 8)
  - Program of musical production involving S. D. and A. I. Ignat'ev. (Folder 1: 9)
    Includes photographs
  - School records (Folder 1: 10)
  - Scrapbook. (Folder 1: 11)
    Includes correspondence and autographs
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 12)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1926-1976
  General note
  See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Scrapbook.
  Includes correspondence to and from Ignat'ev's wife, Aleksandra Ivanovna
  - General
    - General
      - Greeting cards, 1941-1970 (Folder 1: 13)
      - Letters, 1948-1975 (Folder 1: 14)
      - Postcards, 1926-1970 (Box 2)
        - General (Folder 2: 1)
        - Family (Folder 2: 2)
  - Unidentified, 1964-1970 and undated (Folder 2: 3)
  - Alekseev, Pavel I., 1962-1964 and undated (Folder 2: 4)
  - Anna, Igumen'ia, 1959-1965 and undated (Folder 2: 5)
  - Arnemann (?), Vera, 1960-1968 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Associazione Femminile Italiana, 1929 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Barankeev, Ivan, 1963-1971 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Baskakova, L., 1959 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Benigsen, Elena Ivanovna, 1960-1967 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Bogolepov, Aleksei Aleksandrovich, 1961-1970 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Boiarintsev, M., 1961 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Brandt, Guido, 1928-1930 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Cedergren, A. and G., 1952-1964 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Chub, I. A., 1970-1971 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Degtiarev, Mikhail Pavlovich, 1956-1971 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Frömke, Natalia, 1963-1965 (Folder 2: 17)
  - Funk, A., 1963-1964 (Folder 2: 18)
  - Gartong, Marianna, 1960 (Folder 2: 19)
    Includes letter from Gartong to Archbishop Ioann of San Francisco, 1964
  - Gavrilov, Petr E., 1970 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Germany (Federal Republic, 1949-). Generalkonsulat (San Francisco), 1964
  - Ioann, Archbishop of San Francisco, 1946 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Ioann (Pommer), Archbishop of Latvia, 1931 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Iur'eva, M., 1937 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Ivanov, Boris I., 1970 and undated (Folder 3: 4)
  - Kiut (?), N. D., [1929] (Folder 3: 5)
  - Koshlakov, M., Rev., 1942-1976 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Koshlich, Georgii Pavlovich, 1941-1970 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Kozlova, Valentina I., 1970-1976 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Kramarevskaia, V., 1959-1969 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Krivosheev, A., 1961-1965 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Kvartirova, A. and M., 1969 and undated (Folder 3: 11)
  - Ladinskii, Leonid, Rev., 1970-1971 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Langlet, Nina, 1961-1973 (Folder 3: 13)
    Includes poem by Valdemar Langlet
  - Leoussoff, Kseniia, 1955 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Levitov, M., 1971-1974 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Lubimtsev, M. and S., 1953-1970 and undated (Folder 3: 16)
  - Mantulin, Valentin N., 1969 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Mikhailichenko, Vasilii Stepanovich, 1963 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Ob"edinenie russkikh natsional'nykh organizatsii v Germanii, 1936-1937 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Obshchestvo byvshikh dieiatelei Imperatorskago rossiiskago krasnago kresta v Germanii, 1940 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Olen', I., 1955-1961 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Petrenko, N., 1970-1971 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Petrova, Lidiia, 1960-1963 (Folder 3: 23)
  - Pol', V., 1961-1962 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Polozhenskii, Sergei, Rev., 1942-1972 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Sakharov, D., 1936-1961 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Scholuch, A., 1965 (Folder 3: 27)
  - Sergiia, Matushka, 1968 and undated (Folder 3: 28)
  - Smolenskii, Sergei A., 1961-1970 (Folder 3: 29)
  - Snarskaia, Liubov' Ivanovna, 1940-1968 and undated (Folder 3: 30)
  - Timashev, A., 1937-1960 (Folder 3: 31)
  - Tolstaia, M., 1954-1962 (Folder 3: 32)
  - Ugriumov, Aleksei Ivanovich, 1967-1968 (Folder 3: 33)
    Includes related letter by A. Pliushkova
  - Ustinova, Ritta, 1973 (Folder 3: 34)
  - Varashkevich, Boris, 1943 (Folder 3: 35)
  - Veiglas, Nikolai, Rev., 1968-1972 (Folder 3: 36)
  - Verevkina, Mariia, 1964-1968 (Folder 3: 37)
  - Voronkova, S., 1960-1961 (Folder 3: 38)
    Includes related letter by unidentified correspondent
  - Zhdanov, Nikita Romanovich, 1961-1970 (Folder 3: 39)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1917-1966
  - General
    - General. (Folder 3: 40)
      Includes various notes and miscellaneous writings, mainly relating to Russian church music, n.d. Holograph and typescript
    - Letters to the editor, 1966 and undated (Folder 3: 41)
    - Musical compositions
      - General
        - Copyrights to musical notes (Folder 3: 42)
        - Miscellany. (Folder 3: 43)
          Includes lists of notes for balalaika orchestras and similar material
      - "Dosug v dieistvuiushchei armii: Niechto v rodie dnevnika,"., 1917 (Folder 3: 44)
        Holograph
      - S nami Bog, 1966 (Folder 3: 45)
        Printed copy
    - Poetry, 1949-1962 and undated (Folder 4: 1-3)
      May include poems not authored by Ignat'ev, but which he set to music
  - "Adiutantik,", n.d. (Folder 4: 4)
  - "Bogoslovie v zvukakh,", n.d. (Folder 4: 5)
    Typescript
  - "D. S. Bortnianskii,", n.d. (Folder 4: 6)
    Typescript. Includes background materials and typed notes on Bortnianskii's operas
  - "Gallipoliiskii pamiatnik,", n.d. (Folder 4: 7)
    Notes and typescript
  - "Kniaz' Igor',", n.d. (Folder 4: 8)
  - "O Glazunovie,", n.d. (Folder 4: 9)
    Background notes and holograph
  - "Palestrina,", n.d. (Folder 4: 10)
  - "Pamiatnik,", n.d. (Folder 4: 11)
    Printed copy (possibly from Chasovoi)
  - "Pskovitianka,", n.d. (Folder 4: 12)
  - Untitled reminiscences of N. V. Plevitskaia, n.d. (Folder 4: 13)
  - "Kratkoe rukovodstvo k prakticheskomu izucheniiu Oktoikh ili Osmoglasnika,"., 1947 (Folder 4: 14)
  - "Ringaren," Katrineholms-Kuriren,, and Svenska Dagbladet, 1953 December 22 1953 December 27 (Folder 4: 15)
    Printed copies
  - "Glinka,", 1957 (Box 5)
    - Notes and background materials (Folder 5: 1-2)
    - Typescript (Folder 5: 3)
  - "Khor Kubanskikh kazakov u Gosudaryni-Imperatritsy," Russkaia zhizn, 1958 November 25 (Folder 5: 4)
  - "A. G. Rubinshtein,"., [1959] (Folder 5: 5)
  - "Chistyi Chetverg v osazhdennom Berline," Russkaia zhizn', 1966 April 16 (Folder 5: 6)
    Typescript and printed copy
- SUBJECT FILE, 1927-1974
  Correspondence, notes, and printed matter
  - Church of the Transfiguration, Stockholm, Sweden (Folder 5: 7)
  - Glück, Christian (Folder 5: 8)
  - Haydn, Franz-Josef (Folder 5: 9)
  - Holy Trinity Cathedral, San Francisco, California (Folder 5: 10)
  - Kubanskii kazachii khor (Folder 5: 11)
  - Liadov, A. K. (Folder 5: 12)
  - Lissenko, Georg (Folder 5: 13)
  - Obshchestvo russkikh veteranov Velikoi voiny, San Francisco, California (Folder 5: 14)
  - Orthodox Eastern Church--Hymns (Folder 5: 15)
  - Rakhmaninov, S. V. (Folder 5: 16)
  - Religion (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Rimskii-Korsakov, N. A. (Folder 6: 2)
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' (Orthodox Eastern Church) (Folder 6: 3-6)
  - Serov, A. N. (Folder 6: 7)
  - Voice (Folder 6: 8)
  - Miscellany (Folder 6: 9)
  - PRINTED MATTER, 1898-1974 (Box 7)
    Relates to Cossacks, Russian culture, military history and miscellaneous subjects
  - Bulletins (Folder 7: 1)
  - Clippings (Folder 7: 2-3)
  - Periodicals (Folder 7: 4)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, c. 1910-1974 (Box 8)
  - Albums. (Folder 8: 1-6)
    Photographs primarily of Ignat'ev and his ensemble on tour, family members, and miscellaneous events and places
  - Prints (Box 9)
    - Ignat'ev, Semen Dmitrievich (Folder 9: 1)
    - Ignat'eva, Aleksandra Ivanovna (Folder 9: 2)
    - Family photographs (Folder 9: 3-5)
    - Kuban' Cossack Chorus and balalaika orchestra (Folder 9: 6-7)
    - Miscellany
      - Group photographs, which may include Ignat'ev and his wife (Folder 9: 8)
      - Miscellany (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Negatives (1 packet, 3 boxes and 7 booklets) (Folder 10: 2)
- ARTWORK, n.d. (Folder 10: 3)
- FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1927-1974 (Folder 10: 4)
  Bank statements, receipts, financial calculations and other matter. Not filmed